Welcome back to our course. Now today, we're going to be diving deeper into TypeScript
classes focusing particularly on what's called getters and setters. Now these are special
methods that allow us to control access to the properties of a class. And these help us
encapsulate logic as well as validate data and they can even compute values on the fly.
Before we start looking at them, let's have a quick reminder of how we actually construct
a class in TypeScript. So the classes of our blueprints for creating objects. So let's
just quickly knock up an example. So let's do an example of a person. So we define the
class like this with the keyword class. And then we create a constructor. If you
want to, of course, and we may want to pass in the name of the person. So we can do name string.
And if you want to then store that value, we then create ourselves a property inside the
class by doing the name with the property. In this case, it is name and find a type of string.
And then we can actually store the value of or assign the value coming in by the parameter
by doing this dot name equals name. Now this property here by default is a public variable.
So this property here is public by default. And we can also define any methods we want.
Let's have a method called greet. And we can do whatever code we want in here. So let's
do console log. So hello. Hello. Hello. My name is dollar. This dot name. Now to actually
create an instance of that class, we do a const, say, for example, person one equals new.
Then give it the name of the class. In this case, person. And then we can define any parameter
you've got, for example, Alice. And then we can just simply create or, sorry, if they
can simply call the method by just doing person one and we have, like, greet. Okay. So as
I said, name is a public property, meaning it can be accessed and modified directly. So we
could do person dot name and we could change the name, of course, to something like Mary.
Now, while direct access is fine, sometimes we want to control or validate when we're reading
or writing values. So getters allows us to read a property value with some custom logic and
setters allow us to write or update a property we have checks or any transformations that we want.
So let's now add some getters to this particular class. We're going to first of all,
change the accessibility of this property from a public to a private. We can just do private
and we're going to just put a underscore, this changes name just to make it more obvious it's
private. I'm just going to fix our code here by doing this dot name here. And now we can create
ourselves a getter. So we can do that by using the get keyword. So get, then the actual name of the
getter. So in this case, we want to give it call its name. And then we're going to define the return
type of the getter. So string. And now we can actually return a value. So we do return
return this underscore name. Then we can do what if we want. So we could for example, we can
manipulate this and let's say you want to put it in uppercase, just do two uppercase.
Or we could maybe capitalize it or we could make it snake case or anything like that.
Now notice that we no longer can assign any value or directly to the object.
What we could do is just simply act with the name of the person. So we could do a console
log and then we're going to say log person dot name. That's not person. It's person one dot name.
That's going to then output Alice. Let's just execute that. Now we have Alice in our log over here.
So by making our properties private, this becomes effectively encapsulation.
It's the term for this encapsulation. So the getter itself does not require any parentheses
when being accessed. Now we've talked about getters. So let's now talk about
status. So a setter, as you can guess, allows us to control how property is actually modified
and allows us to set a value. So let's now come into here our class and we're going to this
time add a setter. We can do by calling this set. So set. Let's give it a set of age
and we can provide the value for the age, which is in number.
And now we can provide any custom logic we want to validate that value. So we don't want to
make sure that the age is not less than zero. That would mean they're not born, which is kind of
weird. So let's just do to a validation do console log to say age cannot be negative.
And could happen else and say this dot age. And we've got to actually define the variable,
which is would help at all. So let's just do private underscore age and set that to a number.
And now this dot age equals the value being passed in.
Now of course we can come in here and we could do something like a person one dot age equals
let's try and set it to minus five. If we execute that age cannot be negative. Nice.
Now let's do pay attention person one dot age and let's set it to something sensible like 30.
Now you can output that age so console log person dot age. Again, no brackets to call this.
I keep typing person when I want person one. So we're getting undefined now have I think from
moment why you might think this is undefined rather than outputting the person's age.
Now at the moment we have this method to setter that's just accepting a value and is assigning
the value to the age. But we actually have no way or no getter equivalent to actually read
the age. So because it's only a setter we need to also have a get as well to get age.
It's going to return number. Now we simply just do return this age.
Now let's execute it again and we get our age of 30.
So this could be a trap that you fall into to make sure when you have a setter and you want to
read a value you need to have a corresponding age method as well. So in summary I'll get this
can be used to read property values and can also format or compute any values before returning
whereas setters allow us to write property values and it can also validate or transform settings.
As we saw if you have a setter and you want to read the value you'd also need to have a
corresponding age. And notice we also have a little warning here that we've not actually created
initializer. So to get rid of this little error we can cause to age number and we can let's sort
of set a default value. We can neither do it by this underscore age. We can set an age to say
zero if we wanted to or we can actually set a default value here. Then we can just assign it
coming in.